Guide to the MacDowell Club of New York City Records 1905-1942 MS 2953
New-York Historical Society
MacDowell Club of New York City Records
1905-1942
New-York Historical Society
MS 2953
359
13 Linear feet (18 boxes, 22 volumes, 3 oversize folders)
This collection includes minute books, scrapbooks, and other records of the MacDowell Club of New York City (1906-1945), founded in honor of composer Edward MacDowell to foster appreciation of the fine arts. The club played a significant role in the artistic life of the city in the first half of the 20th century.
Provenance
Gift of MacDowell Club of New York City, 1943
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes minute books, account books, membership lists, annual reports, and scrapbooks and other loose ephemera relating to the MacDowell Club of New York City. Scrapbooks include items relating to both the club's internal governance (meetings, member applications, annual reports, etc.) and to club-sponsored public events, such as exhibits, lectures and performances. The collection includes only a very small amount of correspondence. Materials span the period from the club's formation in 1905 until it was dissolved in 1942.
A more complete description of the materials will be found in the scope and contents notes for the individual series.
Biographical / Historical
The MacDowell Club of New York City was founded in 1905 in honor of composer Edward MacDowell, and became a significant force in the artistic and cultural life of the city until it disbanded in 1942.
Edward MacDowell (1860-1908) was one of the first American composers to achieve international fame. Born in New York City, he studied music abroad and eventually returned to New York to serve as the first professor of music at Columbia University in 1896. He resigned in 1904, as a result of disagreement about the role of the music department. After his much-publicized departure, MacDowell's mental and physical health declined rapidly. A handsom cab accident contributed to his growing dementia, and in 1908 MacDowell died at the age of 48.
Before his death, MacDowell's friends and colleagues formed the MacDowell Club of New York City to support the composer and promote his ideals. The purpose of the club, as set forth in its articles of incorporation, was:
"To discuss and demonstrate the principles of the arts of music, literature, the drama, painting, sculpture, and architecture, and to aid in the extension of knowledge of works especially fitted to exemplify the finer purposes of these arts, including works deserving wider recognition, and to promote a sympathetic understanding of the correlation of these arts, and to contribute to the broadening of their influences; thus carrying forward the life purpose of Edward MacDowell."
To fulfill these objectives, the club showcased the arts with performances, recitals, exhibitions and lectures. Within a few years, the club's membership reached 600. Its earliest meetings were held in a studio at Carnegie Hall; from 1909 to 1911, the Club was housed in the Metropolitan Opera House; in October, 1911, the Club established its own club rooms at 108 West 55th Street, where it remained until 1924; and its last home was at 166 East 73rd Street.
In 1911, under the leadership of its second president, John W. Alexander, the Club made headlines with its revolutionary "open" exhibition policy, a radical departure from the normal juried exhibitions. Under this system, self-organized groups of artists could exhibit self-selected works in the Club's galleries at very little expense. Many gifted artists like Stuart David, Edward Hopper, Yasho Kuniyeshi and scores of others had their first exhibitions at the MacDowell Club.
The club's roster of presidents included distinguished artists, musicians, and men of affairs who were patrons of art and accomplished amateurs: Eugene Heffley, John W. Alexander, Frederick Stokes, Ernest Peixotto, Frederick S. Dellenbaugh, Benjamin Prince, Cecil Smith, Hartwell Cahell. Among its members were many well known writers, artists, musicians, actors and architects, including: Hamlin Garland, Richard Watson Gilder, Edwin Arlington Robinson, James Havery Robinson, John Dewey, Leonora Speyer, Herbert Adams, Robert Aitken, Hobart Nichols, Irving Wiles, Ivan Olinsky, Luis Mora, Robert Henri, George Bellows, Louise Homer, David Bispham, Katherine Bacon, Francis Rogers, Charles and Ivah Willis Coburn, Harriet Rogers Otis Dellenbaugh, Beatrice Cameron (Mrs. Richards Mansfield), Harold Van Buren Magonigle.
Early on the club established a Student Fund Committee, which provided timely aid to a whole generation of promising young artists. For many years, the Club maintained a resident fellowship in Professor George Baker's Drama Workshop at Harvard University, as well as a resident scholarship at the MacDowell Colony at Peterborough, New Hampshire. (Although founded at about the same time, by many of the same people, the MacDowell Club of New York also remained a separate entity from the MacDowell Colony, which still exists today).
Another interesting aspect of the club was the early work of the committee on drama. Committee members attended the first performance of noteworthy plays, and if they judged the work favorably, issued a one-page report commenting on the general idea of the play, its characterization, plot, situations, dialogue, production and acting. These reports were sent to club members, who were encouraged with coupons to attend within the first three weeks so as to support the production during this critical early period. A letter from Parker Fillmore, secretary of the club at the time of its dissolution, suggests that this committee became the nucleus of the national Drama League of America.
In 1909, composer Kurt Schindler formed the MacDowell Chorus, which performed with the New York Philharmonic and later became the Scola Contorum.
The MacDowell Club of New York City was one of a number of local MacDowell Clubs that grew up around the country, each of which operated separately from the others.
- Series I: Minutes, 55695
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes a complete set of the minutes of monthly, annual and special meetings of the directors of the MacDowell Club of New York City from the time of its inception until it was dissolved. Minutes of some meetings of several of the club's special committees (Admissions Committee, House Committee, and Student Fund Committee) are also included.
  The minutes, originally stored in binders, have been disbound and rehoused in folders. Loose ephemera and correspondence found in several of the earlier binders will be found in Series IV, Scrapbooks and Ephemera.
  - General minutes, 1905 October - 1906 January; 55707 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General minutes, 1906 January - 1907 March; 55708 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General minutes, 1907 April - 1908 April; 55709 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General minutes, 1908 April - 1909 September; 55710 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General minutes, 1909 October - 1910 May; 55711 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General minutes, 1910 October - 1911 September; 55712 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General minutes, 1911 September - 1912 May; 55713 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General minutes, 1918 October - 1919 May; 55760 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General minutes, 1912 October - 1913 November; 55732 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General minutes, 1913 December - 1914 April; 55733 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General minutes, 1914 October - 1915 October; 55734 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General minutes, 1915 November - 1916 April; 55735 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General minutes, 1916 October - 1917 May; 55736 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - General minutes, 1917 October - 1918 May; 55737 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - General minutes, 1919 October - 1920 May; 55761 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General minutes, 1920 October - 1921 May; 55762 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General minutes, 1921 October - 1922 May; 55763 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General minutes, 1922 October - 1923 April; 55764 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General minutes, 1923 October - 1924 June; 55765 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General minutes, 1924 October - 1925 May; 55766 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - General minutes, 1925 October - 1927 March; 55767 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General minutes, 1927 April - 1928 May; 55768 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General minutes, 1928 April - 1929 May; 55769 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General minutes, 1929 October - 1931 April; 55770 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General minutes, 1931 April - 1934 January; 55771 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General minutes, 1934 April - 1937 April; 55772 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - General minutes, 1937 May - 1941 April; 55773 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - General minutes; Certificate of Dissolution, 1941 - 1944; 1945 January 30; 55774 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Admissions Committee Minutes, 1910-1927; 55775 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - House Committee Minutes, 1908-1922; 55776 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Student Fund Committee Minutes, 1913-1926; 55777 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series II: Account Books, 55703
  This series includes an incomplete set of account books detailing some of the financial operations (receipts and disbursements) of the organization in the 1920's and 1930's.
  - Account book, 1925 April - 1928 March; 57345 (Volume 1)
  - Account book, 1925 - 1927; 57343 (Volume 2)
  - Executive secretary's cashbook, 1929 April - 1932 October; 57346 (Volume 3)
  - Treasurer's cash book, 1929 April - 1933 April; 57344 (Volume 4)
  - Check receipts, 1926 March - 1927 December; 57347 (Volume 5)
  - Check receipts, 1927 December - 1929 April; 57348 (Volume 6)
  - Check receipts, 1929 April - 1930 December; 57349 (Volume 7)
  - Check receipts, 1931 January - 1932 November; 57350 (Volume 8)
  - Check receipts, 1926 November 30 - 1932 July; 57352 (Volume 9)
  - Check receipts, 1932 July - November; 57351 (Volume 10)
  - Check receipts (interest on club bonds), 1924 June - 1925 September; 57353 (Volume 11)
  - Check receipts (interest on club bonds), 1926 May - 1928 May; 57354 (Volume 12)
  - Check receipts (interest on club bonds), 1928 May - 1929 May; 57355 (Volume 13)
- Series III: Membership lists and annual reports, 55704
  This series includes both a cumulative ledger of members and proposed members, and annual lists of members from 1911-1934. Also included are annual reports for the years from 1910 to 1924.
  - List of Members, No. 1, 1906 - ?; 57369 (Volume 14)
  - Proposals for membership, 1909 - 1934; 57370 (Volume 15)
  - List of members, 1907, 1911-1916, 1918, 1919, 1921-1934; 57376 (Box 6)
  - Annual reports, 1910, 1911, 1913-1925; 57377 (Box 7)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks and Ephemera, 55702
  This series consists primarily of annual scrapbooks containing ephemera relating to the club's events and activities. For conservation purposes, most of the scrapbooks have been disbound and re-housed in folders. Examples of the original binding are included in the series.
  The scrapbooks contain items relating to the club's internal activities (meetings, member applications and lists, annual reports, annual dinners, etc.) as well as club-sponsored public events including concerts and recitals, art exhibits, and lectures on drama, literature and other artistic topics. Many examples of the drama committee's reports on plays (described in the Biographical/Historical note of this finding aid) are included. There is also ephemera relating to the club's annual Christmas Festival. Some scrapbooks contain material relating to the Edward MacDowell Memorial Association in New Hampshire, including programs for an elaborate historical pageant performed in his honor.
  Materials represented include programs, notices, announcements, bulletins, invitations, coupons, menus, postcards and reviews and other types of clippings. Several scrapbooks that are comprised almost entirely of newspaper clippings were not disbound and were assigned volume numbers.
  This series also includes several folders of loose ephemera and a small amount of correspondence found in some of the club's early minutes books.
  - Scrapbook 1905-1909, 1905 December 5 - 1909 June 1; 57403 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Loose ephemera from minutes book, 1905-1906, 1911-192; 57402 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 1909-1910, 1909 October - 1910 June; 57407 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
  - Scrapbook 1910-1911, 1910 October - 1911 June; 57393 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Scrapbook 1911-1912, 1911 October - 1912 June; 57401 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 1912-1913, 1912 October - 1913 June; 57409 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Scrapbook 1913-1914, 1913 October - 1914 June; 57408 (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Scrapbook 1914-1915, 1914 October - 1915 June; 57410 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 1915-1916, 1915 October - 1915 June; 57487 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Scrapbook 1916-1917, 1916 October - 1917 June; 57488 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 1917-1918, 1917 June - 1918 October; 57489 (Box 11, Folder 3-4)
  - Scrapbook 1918-1919, 1918 October - 1919 June; 57448 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
  - Loose ephemera from minutes book, 1918-1919; 57491 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook 1919-1920, 1919 October - 1920 June; 57466 (Box 12, Folder unknown container)
  - Scrapbook 1922-1926, 1922 November - 1926 April; 57467 (Box 13, Folder unknown container)
  - Loose ephemera and correspondence, Students Fund Committee, 1921-1926; 57492 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 1926-1929, 1926 October - 1929 June; 57468 (Box 14, Folder 2-5)
  - Scrapbook 1929-1930, 1929 October - 1930 June; 57469 (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook 1930-1931, 1930 October - 1931 June; 57471 (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
  - Scrapbook 1931-1932, 1931 October - 1932 June; 57472 (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
  - Scrapbook 1932-1933, 1932 October - 1933 June; 73465 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 1933-1934, 1933 October - 1934 June; 57473 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
  - Scrapbook 1934-1935, 1934 October - 1935 June; 57474 (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
  - Scrapbook 1935-1936, 1935 October - 1936 June; 57475 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook 1936-1937, 1936 October - 1937 June; 57476 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
  - Scrapbook 1937-1938, 1937 October - 1938 June; 73466 (Box 17, Folder 5-7)
  - Scrapbook 1938-1939, 1938 October - 1939 June; 57477 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - Scrapbook 1939-1940, 1939 October - 1940 June; 57478 (Box 18, Folder 4-6)
  - Scrapbook 1940-1941, 1940 October - 1941 June; 57479 (Volume 16)
  - Scrapbook 1941-1942, 1941 October - 1942 June; 57480 (Volume 17)
  - Scrapbook 1941-1942 (removed loose and oversize material), 82989 (Oversize Small, Folder MacDowell OS1)
  - Scrapbook (reviews and news clippings), 1908-1911; 57411 (Volume 18)
  - Scrapbook (reviews and news clippings), 1911-1912; 57412 (Volume 19)
  - Scrapbook (reviews and news clippings), 1912-1914; 57413 (Volume 20)
  - Scrapbook (reviews and news clippings), 1914-1915; 57414 (Volume 21)
  - Scrapbook, Reports on Plays, 1910-1911; 57482 (Oversize Small, Folder MacDowell OS2)
  - Scrapbook, Theater and Concert Programs, 1910-1911; 57483 (Volume 22)
  - Scrapbook, Drama Committee, 1911-1912; 57481 (Oversize Small, Folder MacDowell OS3)